Finding Aid for the Howard Besser Museum Educational Site Licensing Project Papers, 1983, 1992-1999, and undated IA20019
Institutional Records and Archives
Museum Educational Site Licensing Project papers
1983, 1992-1999, undated (bulk 1996-1998)
1996-1998
Institutional Records and Archives
Columbia University
Cornell University
George Eastman House
Getty Art History Information Program
American University (Washington, D.C.)
Andrew W. Mellon Foundation
Besser, Howard
Museum Educational Site Licensing Project
MUSE Film and Television
Library of Congress
Harvard University. Art Museums
Sandore, Beth
National Museum of American Art (U.S.)
National Gallery of Art (U.S.)
Museum of Fine Arts, Houston
University of Maryland at College Park
University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
University of California, Los Angeles. Fowler Museum of Cultural History
Trant, Jennifer
Yamashita, Robert
University of Virginia
University of Michigan
IA20019
4.77 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
Papers consist of reports, printed matter, correspondence, letters, memoranda, notes, surveys, agenda, minutes, legal documents, and photographs, 1983, 1992-1999 and undated (bulk 1996-1998), created and used by Howard Besser, Principal Investigator and other participants in the Museum Educational Site Licensing Project, sponsored in part by the Getty Art History Information Program. The records describe the genesis, development, execution, and evaluation of the project.
Acquisition Information
The records in this finding aid originated in accession 2002.IA.05, donated by Howard Besser, Principal Investigator for the Museum Educational Site Licensing Project.
Restrictions on Access
The records in accession 2002.IA.05, subject to review for permanently closed information, are open to qualified researchers. Requests for access will be reviewed on a case-by-case basis.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
Papers consist of reports, publications, correspondence, letters, memoranda, notes, forms, surveys and questionnaires, brochures, pamphlets, clippings, press releases, agenda, minutes, invoices, contracts, and photographs, 1983, 1992-1999 and undated (bulk 1996-1998), created and used by participants in the Museum Educational Site Licensing Project, and collected by Howard Besser, Principal Investigator. The records describe the genesis, development, execution, and evaluation of the Project. The bulk of the records describe the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation-funded phase of the Project.
The reports and proposals included in the records outline the methodology for, and provide summary information about, the Project and its results during its Andrew W. Mellon Foundation-funded phase. Included are the grant proposal, written and submitted by Howard Besser, Principal Investigator, to the Mellon Foundation requesting funds to study the economic aspects of the MESL Project; technical reports submitted by the participating institutions; and two versions of the final report, The Cost of Digital Image Distribution: The Social and Economic Implications of the Production, Distribution and Usage of Image Data, authored by Howard Besser and Robert Yamashita (Project Manager).
The data gathering records describe the selection process for participating institutions and provide information about the design and results of data gathering. The materials contain the institutional applications of the University of Virginia, American University, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, University of Maryland at College Park, University of Michigan, Columbia University, the Fowler Museum of Cultural History, George Eastman House, Harvard University Art Museums, the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, Library of Congress, National Gallery of Art, and the National Museum of American Art.
The evaluation process funded through the Mellon Foundation, which focused on the economic implications of the Project, is documented through surveys and questionnaires completed by the participating institutions. These records also contain documents describing the development of the evaluation process, the evaluation itself, and its results. These records contain correspondence between Besser, Jennifer Trant, Beth Sandore (consultant), and other individuals involved in the evaluation.
Finally, the records contain publications and presentations produced by Howard Besser and participants in the Museum Educational Site Licensing Project, provide information about administrative matters related to the execution of the Project (specifically the Project's Advisory Board, meeting minutes, budget and expense information, and personnel records), and contain research and background materials collected by Howard Besser.
Organization
These records are organized in six series: Series I. Proposals and reports, 1992-1999; Series II. Gathered data, 1994-1998; Series III. Evaluation materials, 1995-1998 and undated; Series IV. Publications and presentations, 1995-1999; Series V. Administrative records, 1995-1999 and undated; Series VI. Research and background materials, 1983, 1992, 1994-1998 and undated.
Administrative History
The Museum Educational Site Licensing (MESL) Project (1994-1997) was designed to explore the feasibility of networked distribution of digital museum content in educational settings. The Project grew out of two meetings held in March 1994, the first was sponsored by the Getty Art History Information Program (AHIP), and the second by MUSE Educational Media. The AHIP meeting's purpose was to announce the launch of a digital imaging initiative; the MUSE meeting's purpose was to discuss the results of a study for developing model licensing agreements for digital media on CD-ROMs. Detailed planning for the MESL Project took place during the summer of 1994 and involved David Bearman (President, Archives and Museum Informatics), Howard Besser (Associate Professor, Information and Library Studies, University of Michigan), Eleanor Fink (Director, AHIP), Geoffrey Samuels (Director, MUSE Museum Multimedia Study Group), and Jennifer Trant (Consultant, and Manager of the Imaging Initiative, AHIP).
The MESL Project was originally framed as a testbed demonstration project to bring together museums and universities to explore the administrative, legal, economic, technical and educational issues surrounding networked distribution of museum content for educational use. The organizational phase of the project was supported by AHIP and MUSE Educational Media. The second phase of the Project was supported by a grant from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, and focused on studying the costs and benefits of networked distribution of digital museum information for educational use.
The Project was officially launched in September 1994 with the initial call for participation. Over 80 museums and universities submitted applications; 6 cultural institutions and 7 universities were chosen by the Project's Managing Committee. The cultural institutions were: The Fowler Museum of Cultural History, UCLA; George Eastman House; Harvard University Art Museums; the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston; the National Gallery of Art; and the National Museum of American Art. In 1995, the Library of Congress was added. The 7 universities were: American University; Columbia University; Cornell University; University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign; University of Maryland at College Park; University of Michigan—Ann Arbor, Dearborn and Flint; and the University of Virginia.
Pictures in education -- United States -- Data processing; Clippings (information artifacts); Surveys (documents); Forms (documents); Picture archiving and communication systems -- United States; Reports; Contracts; Art -- Computer network resources; Memorandums; Press releases; Notes; Letters (correspondence); Agendas (administrative records); Pamphlets; Correspondence; Publications; Minutes; Questionnaires; Photographs; Invoices; Brochures
- Proposals and reports, 1995-1999; (bulk 1996-1997); Series I.; 1.25 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  These records are arranged in general chronological order.
  Scope and Contents note
  Papers consist of reports, proposals and correspondence, 1992-1999, of the Museum Educational Site Licensing Project that outline the methodology for, and provide summary information about, the Project and its results during its Andrew W. Mellon Foundation-funded phase. Included are the grant proposal, written and submitted by Howard Besser, Principal Investigator, to the Mellon Foundation requesting funds to study the economic aspects of the MESL Project; the museum and university technical reports, which describe the technical issues involved in the dissemination of MESL content and report on the experience; a draft of MESL Perspectives, published simultaneously with the final report, and providing "unofficial insights" into the Project; a draft of the final report submitted to the Mellon Foundation; and two versions of the final report, The Cost of Digital Image Distribution: The Social and Economic Implications of the Production, Distribution and Usage of Image Data, authored by Howard Besser and Robert Yamashita (Project Manager). The final report originally appeared in July 1998 and was reprinted in June 1999.
  Some duplication appears within the records.
  - Mellon—proposals, correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 1)
  - Mellon grant, 1995-1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 2)
  - Original grant proposal, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 3)
  - Proposal drafts and supporting documents, 1996; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 4-5)
  - Proposal, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 6)
  - Proposal (annotated), circa 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 7)
  - MESL description, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 8)
  - Report to advisory board, November 18, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 9)
  - Project materials, 1. MESL information, 1996; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 10-11)
  - "MESL Data Dictionary,", 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 12)
  - Technical report development, 1996-1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 13)
  - Museum technical reports, 1996-1997; [7 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 14-20)
  - Project materials, volume 1: Management:
    - 1997, [1-3 of 4 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-1, Folder 21-23)
    - 1997, [4 of 4 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-2, Folder 1)
  - Museum technical reports (project materials, volume 2):, 1996-1997; [9 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-2, Folder 2-10)
  - Content selection in the MESL Project, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-2, Folder 11)
  - University technical reports, 1997; [8 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-2, Folder 12-19)
  - American University technical report:
    - March 13, 1997, [1-3 of 4 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-2, Folder 20-22)
    - March 13, 1997, [4 of 4 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 1)
  - Technical report, University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 2)
  - Museum report draft, undated (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 3)
  - MESL terms and conditions, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 4)
  - Interim draft report and letter, 1997; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 5-6)
  - Final report draft introduction, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 7)
  - MESL Perspectives, 1997; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 8-9)
  - Proposed contents, final report, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 10)
  - Final report:
    - Project background and history, 1997-1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 11)
    - Terms and conditions–framing the issues, 1997-1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 12)
    - Terms and conditions–issues, 1997-1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 13)
    - Terms and conditions–summary of issues, 1997-1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 14)
    - Content selection, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 15)
    - Technical issues introduction, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 16)
    - MESL data dictionary and data export process, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 17)
    - Digital image production issues, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 18)
    - The MESL distribution process, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 19)
    - Use and impact, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 20)
    - MESL impact: museum perspective, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 21)
    - MESL impact: university perspective, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 22)
    - Summary report, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 23)
    - MESL casual user survey, July 11, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 24)
    - Executive summary, July 15, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 25)
    - Introduction [to Economics section], circa 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 26)
  - Annotated draft reports, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 27)
  - Final report notes, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 28)
  - Howard Besser and Robert Yamashita, The Cost of Digital Image Distribution, July 1998; [3 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 29-31)
  - Richard Ekman correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 32)
  - Howard Besser and Robert Yamashita, The Cost of Digital Image Distribution, June 1999; [3 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-3, Folder 33-35)
  - Howard Besser and Robert Yamashita, The Cost of Digital Image Distribution, June 1999; [3 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 1-3)
    General note
    [2nd printing.]
  - MESL art production guidelines, undated (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 4)
  - Robert Yamashita, Chapter 1, Background, undated (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 5)
  - Stephenson, Christie, Patricia McClung, eds. Delivering Digital Images: Cultural Heritage Resources for Education (The Museum Educational Site Licensing Project, Volume I) Los Angeles: The Getty Information Institute, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 6)
  - Stephenson, Christie, Patricia McClung, eds. Images Online: Perspectives on the Museum Educational Site Licensing Project (The Museum Educational Site Licensing Project, Volume II) Los Angeles: The Getty Information Institute, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 7)
- Gathered data, 1994-1998; Series II.; 1.25 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
  These records are arranged generally by subject (calls for participation and applications, participation proposals, other information about educational institutions, slide library questionnaires and information, museum institutional profiles, participant meetings, technical data, and focus groups), and chronology.
  Papers consist of surveys, reports, brochures, pamphlets, agendas, and correspondence, 1994-1998, of the Museum Educational Site Licensing Project. The records describe the selection process for participating institutions and contain their applications (specifically, the University of Virginia, American University, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, University of Maryland at College Park, University of Michigan, Columbia University, the Fowler Museum of Cultural History, George Eastman House, Harvard University Art Museums, the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, Library of Congress, National Gallery of Art, and the National Museum of American Art). The records also provide information about the design and results of data gathering among participating institutions and several other universities and information about and from participant meetings held in Santa Monica, California and Washington, D.C.
  For additional information on the Santa Monica participant's meetings, see also Series V. Administrative records.
  - Call for participation drafts, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 8)
  - MUSE letters, call for participation, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 9)
  - Educational institution applications, 1994; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 10-11)
  - Museum applications, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous MESL emails, 1995 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 13)
  - MESL meeting agenda, background information, 1995 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 14)
  - Patti McClung, conference call notes, 1995 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 15)
  - Conference call notes, 1995-1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 16)
  - Mellon documents, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 17)
    [Notes and emails discussing the presentation of data and the preparation of the report to the Mellon Foundation.]
  - MESL Participants, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 18)
  - About MESL, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 19)
    [Includes calls for participation.]
  - University participation proposals:
    - American University, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-4, Folder 20)
    - Columbia University, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 1)
    - Cornell University, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 2)
    - University of Michigan, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 3)
    - University of Virginia, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 4)
  - Other information about educational institutions:
    - University sites, 1995 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 5)
    - Harvard, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 6)
    - University of Maryland, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 7)
    - University of Michigan distribution cost report, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence re: University of Michigan role, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 9)
    - University of Oregon information, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 10)
  - Slide library questionnaires and information:
    - American University, 1997-1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 11)
    - Columbia University, 1997-1998; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 12-13)
    - University of California, Berkeley, Architecture Slide Library, 1997; [4 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 14-17)
    - University of California, Berkeley, Art History Slide Library, 1993-1997; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 18-19)
    - University of Illinois, 1997-1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-5, Folder 20)
    - University of Oregon, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 1)
  - Museum institutional profiles, 1994 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 2)
  - George Eastman House, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 3)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 4)
  - Participant meetings:
    - Participant meetings reports, 1995-1996; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 5-6)
    - Participants meeting, American University, May 13-15, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 7)
    - Agenda, Santa Monica meeting, December 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 8)
    - Discussion drafts, Santa Monica meeting, December 1996; [3 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 9-11)
  - Survey forms, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 12)
    [Drafts of requests for information for technical reports.]
  - Museum "baseline,", 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 13)
    [Notes re: requests for information for technical reports.]
  - Server "monitoring,", 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 14)
    [Emails regarding collection of data from MESL servers.]
  - Focus groups:
    - CAA focus group, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 15)
    - Focus group notes, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 16)
    - Focus group notes and questionnaires, 1998; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 17-18)
    - Focus group transcripts, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 19)
    - Focus group report (draft), 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 20)
    - Focus group notes, undated (Box 2002.IA.05-6, Folder 21)
- Evaluation materials, 1995-1998; undated; Series III.; 0.82 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
  These records are arranged chronologically.
  Papers consist of correspondence, letters, notes, reports, surveys, and questionnaires, 1995-1998 and undated, created by participants, including Howard Besser and Jennifer Trant, in the Museum Educational Site Licensing Project, that describe the development of the evaluation process, the evaluation itself, and its results during the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation-funded phase of the Project. These records include evaluations of use, but are specifically focused on the economic implications of the Project. During this phase of the project, Beth Sandore, Coordinator, Digital Imaging Initiative and Associate Professor, University of Illinois, was hired as a consultant.
  - Letter re: project evaluation proposal, 1995 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 1)
  - Evaluation surveys, 1995; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 2-3)
  - Evaluation, 1995-1996; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 4-5)
  - MESL evaluation, 1995-1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 6)
  - Emails and information re: evaluation, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 7)
  - Workplans, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 8)
  - Evaluation committee, 1996; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 9-10)
  - Beth Sandore's questionnaires, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 11)
  - Measurement responses, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 12)
  - Emails, notes re: evaluation, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 13)
  - Workshop on user needs and assessment and evaluation, DL '96, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous evaluation reports, 1996; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 15-16)
  - Online surveys, 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 17)
  - Instructor/Student/Researcher evaluation and questionnaires, 1996-1997; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 18-19)
  - Art image database instructor and student evaluation report, 1997; [3 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 20-22)
  - Schedule for MESL evaluation visit, University of Illinois, Urbana Champaign, February 10-11, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-7, Folder 23)
  - Evaluation conference call, 4/29, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 1)
  - Post-questionnaires, 1997; [5 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 2-6)
  - Site visits, notes, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 7)
  - Agenda, reports, notes, Charlottesville meeting, May 1997; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 8-9)
  - Charlottesville presentation, May 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 10)
  - Pre/post questionnaires, technical reports, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 11)
  - Evaluation conference call emails, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 12)
  - Evaluation questionnaires, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 13)
  - Instructor and student evaluation report, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 14)
  - Options analysis, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 15)
  - "The Use of an Art Image Database in the Classroom: Instructor and Student Evaluation Report,", 1997; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 16-17)
  - Human subjects, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous slide library notes, 1998; undated (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 19)
- Publications and presentations, 1995-1999; Series IV.; 0.4 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
  Papers consist of publication drafts, publication galleys, photocopies of articles and book chapters, and typescripts of presentations, 1995-1999, produced by participants in the Museum Educational Site Licensing Project. The general subjects of all the documents are issues, challenges, and results of the Project. Many of the articles were printed from the Getty Art History Information Program's website. The majority of the presentations were authored and delivered by Howard Besser, Principal Investigator.
  - MESL produced articles, 1995-1996; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 20-21)
  - "Technical Issues in the Distribution of Museum Images and Textual Data to Universities,", 1996 (Box 2002.IA.05-8, Folder 22)
  - MESL papers, 1996-1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 1)
  - Chapters from The Wired Museum, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 2)
  - Final copies of MESL final report articles, 1997 (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 3)
  - Time and Bits panel, 1997-1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 4)
  - Digital libraries/metadata, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 5)
  - CIL 98 metadata workshop, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 6)
  - CIL 98 digital library talk, 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 7)
  - "UCB Mellon Grant Studying MESL: What Have We Learned about Image Databases and Universities?", circa 1998 (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 8)
  - Visual Resources proof, 1999 (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 9)
  - Annotated copies of Visual Resources articles, 1999; [2 files] (Box 2002.IA.05-9, Folder 10-11)